Allow me to start this talk with a question to everyone.
اسمحوا لي بأن أبدأ هذا الحديث بسؤال أوجهه لكم
You know that all over the world,
تعرفون أن جميع الناس حول العالم
people fight for their freedom,
يقاتلون من أجل حريتهم،
fight for their rights.
يقاتلون من أجل حقوقهم.
Some battle oppressive governments.
البعض تكون معاركهم ضد الحكومات القمعية.
Others battle oppressive societies.
والآخرون ضد المجتمعات القمعية.
Which battle do you think is harder?
أي المعارك التي تعتقدون انها الأصعب؟
Allow me to try to answer this question
اسمحوا لي بأن أحاول أن أجيب على هذا السؤال
in the few coming minutes.
خلال الدقائق القليلة القادمة.
Let me take you back two years ago in my life.
دعوني آخذكم في رحلة شخصية بدأت قبل عامين.
It was the bedtime of my son, Aboody.
كان ذلك في وقت نوم ابني، عبودي.
He was five at the time.
كان يبلغ الخامسة من عمره في ذلك الوقت.
After finishing his bedtime rituals,
بعد أن أنهى جميع طقوس النوم،
he looked at me and he asked a question:
نظر إلي وسألني سؤالا:
"Mommy, are we bad people?"
"أمي، هل نحن أشخاص سيئون؟"
I was shocked.
أصبت بالصدمة.
"Why do you say such things, Aboody?"
"لماذا تقول مثل هذا الكلام، يا عبودي؟"
Earlier that day, I noticed some bruises
في وقت سابق من ذلك اليوم، كنت قد لاحظت كدمات
on his face when he came from school.
على وجهه عندما عاد من المدرسة.
He wouldn't tell me what happened.
لم يخبرني بما حدث له.
[But now] he was ready to tell.
ولكنه الآن، كان مستعدا ليخبرني.
"Two boys hit me today in school.
قال: "ضربني ولدان اليوم في المدرسة.
They told me, 'We saw your mom on Facebook.
وقالوا لي: ’لقد شاهدنا أمك على الفيسبوك.
You and your mom should be put in jail.'"
أنت وأمك يجب أن توضعوا في السجن’".
I've never been afraid to tell Aboody anything.
لم أكن في يوم أخشى أن أخبر عبودي بأي شيء.
I've been always a proud woman of my achievements.
لقد كنت دوما امرأة فخورة بما حققته.
But those questioning eyes of my son
ولكن عيون ابني المتسائلة
were my moment of truth,
كانت تلك هي لحظة الحقيقة بالنسبة لي،
when it all came together.
عندما اجتمعت كل الأشياء مع بعضها.
You see, I'm a Saudi woman who had been put in jail
حسنا، أنا امرأة سعودية تم وضعها في السجن
for driving a car in a country
لقيادتها سيارة في دولة
where women are not supposed to drive cars.
لا يُفترض فيها أن تقود النساء السيارات.
Just for giving me his car keys,
فقط لأنه أعطاني مفاتيح سيارته،
my own brother was detained twice,
فقد اُعتقل أخي مرتين،
and he was harassed to the point he had
وكان دوما في حالة مضايقات للدرجة التي
to quit his job as a geologist,
جعلته يتخلى عن وظيفته كجيولوجي،
leave the country with his wife and two-year-old son.
وأن يتغرّب عن البلاد مع زوجته وابنه ذو العامين.
My father had to sit in a Friday sermon
كان على والدي أن يجلس في خطبة الجمعة
listening to the imam condemning women drivers
ويستمع إلى الإمام وهو يدين و يندد بالنساء اللاتي يقدن السيارات
and calling them prostitutes
ويصفهن بالعاهرات
amongst tons of worshippers,
أمام جمع من المصلين،
some of them our friends and family of my own father.
وبعضهم من أصدقاء ومن أسرة والدي.
I was faced with an organized defamation campaign
واجهت حملة قذف وافتراء منظمة
in the local media combined with false rumors
من قبل الإعلام المحلي وصاحبتها اشاعات مغرضة
shared in family gatherings, in the streets
تم مشاركتها في تجمعات الأسر، في الشوارع،
and in schools.
وفي المدارس.
It all hit me.
وكلها كانت تؤثر فيّ.
It came into focus that those kids
واتضح جليا أن هؤلاء الأطفال
did not mean to be rude to my son.
لم يقصدوا أن يكونو فظين مع ابني.
They were just influenced by the adults around them.
ولكنهم فقط تأثروا بالبالغين من حولهم.
And it wasn't about me, and it wasn't a punishment
ولم يكن ذلك عني أنا، ولم يكن ذلك عقابا
for taking the wheel and driving a few miles.
لأني جلست خلف المقود وقدت لأميال قليلة.
It was a punishment for daring to challenge
كان ذلك عقابا للمقدرة على تحدي
the society's rules.
قوانين المجتمع.
But my story goes beyond this moment of truth of mine.
ولكن قصتي تسير أبعد من لحظة الحقيقة تلك.
Allow me to give you a briefing
اسمحوا لي بأن أعطيكم ملخصا
about my story.
لقصتي.
It was May, 2011,
كان ذلك في مايو، 2011،
and I was complaining to a work colleague
وكنت أتذمر لزميلي في العمل
about the harassments I had to face
عن المضايقات التي يجب أن أمرّ بها
trying to find a ride back home,
في محاولتي لأجد ما يقلني إلى المنزل،
although I have a car and an international driver's license.
وذلك بالرغم من أني أمتلك سيارة ورخصة قيادة دولية.
As long as I've known, women in Saudi Arabia
على حد علمي، فإن النساء في السعودية
have been always complaining about the ban,
لطالما كانوا يتذمرون من هذا المنع،
but it's been 20 years since anyone
و مرّ الآن 20 عاما منذ أن حاول أي أحد
tried to do anything about it,
أن يفعل شيئا حيال هذا الأمر،
a whole generation ago.
جيل كامل قد مضى.
He broke the good/bad news in my face.
وقد أخبرني بالخبر الجيد/السيء في وجهي.
"But there is no law banning you from driving."
"ولكن لا يوجد قانون يمنعك من القيادة."
I looked it up, and he was right.
بحثت عن تلك المعلومة، لقد كان محقا.
There wasn't an actual law in Saudi Arabia.
لم يكن هناك قانون فعلي في السعودية.
It was just a custom and traditions
لقد كان ذلك فقط جزءا من العادات والتقاليد
that are enshrined in rigid religious fatwas
والتي تكرسّت بالفتاوى الدينية الصارمة
and imposed on women.
وطُبقّت على النساء.
That realization ignited the idea of June 17,
تلك الحقيقة هي ما أوقد شرارة فكرة يوم 17 يونيو،
where we encouraged women to take the wheel
والتي عندها، شجّعنا النساء ليجلسوا خلف المقود
and go drive.
ويبدأن بالقيادة.
It was a few weeks later, we started receiving all these
وبعدها بأسابيع قليلة، بدأنا نستقبل كل هذه الرسائل
"Man wolves will rape you if you go and drive."
"ذئاب الرجال سيقومون باغتصابكن إذا كنتن تقدن بأنفسكن".
A courageous woman, her name is Najla Hariri,
امرأة شجاعة، اسمها نجلاء حريري،
she's a Saudi woman in the city of Jeddah,
وهي امرأة سعودية تسكن في جدة،
she drove a car and she announced
قامت بقيادة سيارة وأعلنت عن ذلك
but she didn't record a video.
ولكنها لم تقم بتصوير فيديو.
We needed proof.
كنا في حاجة إلى إثبات.
So I drove. I posted a video on YouTube.
ولذا قمت انا بالقيادة. ولقد حمّلت فيديو لقيادتي على اليوتيوب.
And to my surprise,
ولدهشتي،
it got hundreds of thousands of views the first day.
لقد شاهده مئات الآلاف خلال اليوم الأول.
What happened next, of course?
وبالطبع، ماذا حدث لاحقا؟
I started receiving threats
بدأت أستقبل التهديدات
to be killed, raped, just to stop this campaign.
بالقتل، بالاغتصاب، فقط لكي أوقف هذه الحملة.
The Saudi authorities remained very quiet.
وظلّت السلطات السعودية تلتزم الصمت.
That really creeped us out.
وهو ما حيّرنا.
I was in the campaign with other Saudi women
كنت في هذه الحملة مع نساء سعوديات أخريات
and even men activists.
بل وحتى ناشطون من الرجال.
We wanted to know how the authorities
وكنا نود أن نعرف كيف ستتعامل السلطات
would respond on the actual day, June 17,
مع هذا الأمر في اليوم المقرر للحدث، 17 يونيو،
when women go out and drive.
عندما تخرج النساء للقيادة.
So this time I asked my brother
لذا، في هذه المرة طلبت من أخي
to come with me and drive by a police car.
أن يأتي معي وأن نقود بالقرب من سيارة شرطة.
It went fast. We were arrested,
تم الأمر سريعا. تم اعتقالنا،
signed a pledge not to drive again, released.
وقّعت على تعهد أن لا أقود مرة أخرى، أُفرج عنا.
Arrested again, he was sent to detention for one day,
تم اعتقالنا مجددا، تم ارسال أخي إلى الحجز لمدة يوم واحد،
and I was sent to jail.
وأنا تم إرسالي إلى السجن.
I wasn't sure why I was sent there,
لم أكن واثقة لماذا تم إرسالي إلى هناك،
because I didn't face any charges in the interrogation.
لأنه لم يتم توجيه أي تهمة إلي في أثناء التحقيق.
But what I was sure of was my innocence.
والشيء الذي كنت متأكدة منه هو براءتي.
I didn't break a law, and I kept my abaya
لم أخالف القانون، لذا فمازلت في عباءتي
— it's a black cloak we wear in Saudi Arabia before we leave the house —
- وهي عباءة سوداء نرتديها في السعودية قبل ان نغادر منازلنا -
and my fellow prisoners kept asking me to take it off,
وجميع المسجونات الأخريات ظللن يطلبن مني أن أخلع العباءة،
but I was so sure of my innocence, I kept saying,
ولكني كنت متيقنة من براءتي، لذا ظللت أقول،
"No, I'm leaving today."
"لا داعي، فأنا سأغادر اليوم."
Outside the jail, the whole country went into a frenzy,
خارج السجن، كل المجتمع مرّ بحالة من التخبط،
some attacking me badly,
البعض يهاجمونني بشدة،
and others supportive and even collecting signatures
والبعض الآخر يدعمون بل وحتى يجمعون التوقيعات
in a petition to be sent to the king to release me.
على إلتماس ليرسلوه إلى الملك لكي يُطلق سراحي.
I was released after nine days.
تم إطلاق سراحي بعد 9 أيام.
June 17 comes.
وجاء يوم 17 يونيو.
The streets were packed with police cars
امتلأت الشوارع بسيارات الشرطة
and religious police cars,
وسيارات الهيئة،
but some hundred brave Saudi women
ولكن بضع مئات من نساء السعودية الشجاعات
broke the ban and drove that day.
كسرنّ الحاجز وقادوا في ذلك اليوم.
None were arrested. We broke the taboo.
لم تُعتقل أي منهن. كسرنا حاجز المسكوت عنه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I think by now, everyone knows that we can't drive,
أعتقد انه الآن، كل واحد منكم يعلم أننا لا نستطيع أن نقود،
or women are not allowed to drive, in Saudi Arabia,
أو أن النساء غير مسموح لهن بالقيادة، في السعودية،
but maybe few know why.
ولكن في الأغلب القلة فقط تعرف لماذا.
Allow me to help you answer this question.
اسمحوا لي بأن أساعدكم في الإجابة عن هذا السؤال.
There was this official study
هنالك هذه الدراسة الرسمية
that was presented to the Shura Council --
والتي قُدّمت لمجلس الشورى
it's the consultative council appointed
- وهو مجلس إستشاري يتم تعيينه
by the king in Saudi Arabia —
بواسطة الملك في السعودية -
and it was done by a local professor,
وهذه الدراسة أجريت بواسطة بروفيسور محلي،
a university professor.
أستاذ جامعي.
He claims it's done based on a UNESCO study.
وهو يدّعي بأنها أجريت بناءً على دراسة أجرتها اليونيسكو.
And the study states,
وتقول هذه الدراسة،
the percentage of rape, adultery,
نسب الاغتصاب، الزنا،
illegitimate children, even drug abuse,
أبناء السفاح، وحتى تعاطي المخدرات،
prostitution in countries where women drive
والدعارة في الدول التي تقود فيها النساء السيارات
is higher than countries where women don't drive.
هي نسب أعلى عن الدول التي لا تقود فيها النساء السيارات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I know, I was like this, I was shocked.
أعرف، فقد مررت بهذه الحالة، لقد اندهشت.
I was like, "We are the last country in the world
كنت مثل، "نحن الدولة الأخيرة في العالم
where women don't drive."
التي لا تقود فيها النساء."
So if you look at the map of the world,
لذا إذا نظرتم لخريطة العالم،
that only leaves two countries:
فإن هذا سيترك لنا دولتين فقط:
Saudi Arabia, and the other society is the rest of the world.
السعودية، والمجتمع الآخر هو بقية العالم.
We started a hashtag on Twitter mocking the study,
لقد بدأنا وسما على التويتر نسخر من هذه الدراسة،
and it made headlines around the world.
وتحولت إلى عناوين بارزة حول العالم.
[BBC News: 'End of virginity' if women drive, Saudi cleric warns]
[أخبار بي بي سي: "نهاية العذرية" إذا قادت النساء تحذير رجل دين سعودي]
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And only then we realized it's so empowering
وعندها فقط أدركنا قوة
to mock your oppressor.
السخرية من القامع.
It strips it away of its strongest weapon: fear.
فإنها تعريه من أقوى أسلحته، الخوف.
This system is based on ultra-conservative
هذا النظام مبني على المحافظة المتشددة
traditions and customs
على العادات والتقاليد
that deal with women as if they are inferior
والتي تتعامل مع النساء كما لو انهن أقل مستوى
and they need a guardian to protect them,
وكما لو أنهن بحاجة إلى راع لحمايتهن،
so they need to take permission from this guardian,
لذا يجب عليهن ان يأخذن الإذن من هذا الراعي،
whether verbal or written, all their lives.
سواء كان شفهيا أو مكتوبا، طوال حياتهن.
We are minors until the day we die.
نحن قاصرات حتى يوم وفاتنا.
And it becomes worse when it's enshrined in religious fatwas
ويكون هذا أسوأ عندما تتكرس بالفتاوى الدينية
based on wrong interpretation of the sharia law,
المبنية على التفسيرات الخاطئة لقوانين الشريعة،
or the religious laws.
أو للقوانين الدينية.
What's worst, when they become codified
الأسوأ من هذا هو أن تدوّن
as laws in the system,
كقوانين في النظام،
and when women themselves believe in their inferiority,
وأن تكون النساء أنفسهن يؤمنّ بدونيتهن،
and they even fight those who try
بل وحتى يقاومن هؤلاء الذين يحاولون
to question these rules.
أن يشككوا في هذه القوانين.
So for me, it wasn't only about these attacks I had to face.
بالنسبة لي، لم تكن فقط حول هذه الهجمات التي كنت أواجهها.
It was about living two totally different
بل كانت عن طريقة حياة منظورين مختلفين
perceptions of my personality, of my person --
عن شخصيتي، عن نفسي،
the villain back in my home country,
الشخص الحقير هناك في موطني،
and the hero outside.
والبطل في خارجها.
Just to tell you, two stories happened in the last two years.
فقط لأجعلكم تدركون، قصتان حصلتا خلال السنتين الماضيتين.
One of them is when I was in jail.
الأولى كانت خلال فترة وجودي في السجن.
I'm pretty sure when I was in jail,
أنا متأكدة تماما، أنه وخلال وجودي في السجن،
everyone saw titles in the international media
أي شخص رأى عناوين في وسائل الإعلام العالمية
something like this during these nine days I was in jail.
كانت كهذه خلال الأيام التسعة التي كنت فيها بالسجن.
But in my home country, it was a totally different picture.
ولكن في موطني الأم، كانت الصورة مختلفة تماما.
It was more like this:
كانت كهذه:
"Manal al-Sharif faces charges of disturbing public order
"منال الشريف تواجه تهمة الإخلال بالنظام العام
and inciting women to drive."
وتحريض النساء على القيادة."
I know.
أعرف.
"Manal al-Sharif withdraws from the campaign."
"منال الشريف تنسحب من الحملة."
Ah, it's okay. This is my favorite.
آها، لا بأس. هذه المفضلة لدي.
"Manal al-Sharif breaks down and confesses:
"منال الشريف تنهار وتعترف:
'Foreign forces incited me.'"
’قوي خارجية تحرضني.’"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it goes on, even trial and flogging me in public.
وتتواصل، حتى المحاكمة والجلد في العلن.
So it's a totally different picture.
لذا فهي صورة مختلفة تماما.
I was asked last year to give a speech
لقد طُلب مني في السنة الماضية ان أتحدّث
at the Oslo Freedom Forum.
في منتدى أوسلو للحريات.
I was surrounded by this love
كنت محاطة بهذا الحب
and the support of people around me,
والدعم من الأشخاص الذين من حولي،
and they looked at me as an inspiration.
وكانوا ينظرون إلي كمصدر للإلهام.
At the same time, I flew back to my home country,
وفي نفس الوقت، سافرت عائدة إلى موطني،
they hated that speech so much.
لقد كرهوا ذلك الخطاب لدرجة شديدة.
The way they called it: a betrayal to the Saudi country
لدرجة أنهم وصفوه بالخيانة للدولة السعودية
and the Saudi people,
وللشعب السعودي،
and they even started a hashtag called #OsloTraitor on Twitter.
بل وحتى أنشاووا وسم سموه #خائنة_أوسلو على تويتر.
Some 10,000 tweets were written in that hashtag,
حوالي 10،000 تغريدة كُتبت على ذلك الوسم.
while the opposite hashtag, #OsloHero,
بينما الوسم المضاد، #بطلة_اوسلو،
there was like a handful of tweets written.
فلم يكتب عليه إلا حفنة من التغريدات.
They even started a poll.
بل حتى أنهم قاموا باستطلاع.
More than 13,000 voters answered this poll:
أكثر من 13،000 مشارك قاموا بالتصويت على هذا الاستطلاع:
whether they considered me a traitor or not after that speech.
أيعتبرونني خائنة أم لا بعد ذلك الخطاب.
Ninety percent said yes, she's a traitor.
90 بالمائة أجابوا نعم، إنها خائنة.
So it's these two totally different perceptions
لذا فإن هناك هذين الإدراكين المختلفين
of my personality.
لشخصيتي.
For me, I'm a proud Saudi woman,
بالنسبة لي، أنا امرأة سعودية فخورة،
and I do love my country,
وأحب بلادي،
and because I love my country, I'm doing this.
ولأنني أحب بلادي، فأنا أفعل هذا.
Because I believe a society will not be free
لأنني أؤمن بأن المجتمعات لن تكون حرة
if the women of that society are not free.
إذا لم تكن نساء تلك المجتمعات حرة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
Thank you, thank you, thank you, thank you.
شكرا لكم، شكرا لكم، شكرا لكم، شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
But you learn lessons from these things that happen to you.
ولكنكم تتعلمون دروسا من هذه الأشياء التي تحدث لكم.
I learned to be always there.
تعلمت أكون دوما موجودة.
The first thing, I got out of jail,
أول شيء فعلته عندما خرجت من السجن،
of course after I took a shower, I went online,
بالطبع بعد أن أخذت حماما، كنت على الإنترنت،
I opened my Twitter account and my Facebook page,
فتحت حسابي على تويتر، وصفحتي على الفيسبوك،
and I've been always very respectful
وكنت دوما أحترم أولئك الأشخاص
to those people who are opining to me.
الذين دوما ما كانوا يناقشونني.
I would listen to what they say,
أحب أن أستمع لما يقولون،
and I would never defend myself with words only.
ولم أكن لأدافع عن نفسي بالكلمات فقط.
I would use actions. When they said I should withdraw from the campaign,
بل بالأفعال. عندما طالبوني بالانسحاب من هذه الحملة،
I filed the first lawsuit against the general directorate
قمت برفع أول دعوى قضائية ضد الإدارة العامة
of traffic police for not issuing me a driver's license.
لشرطة المرور لعدم إصدارهم رخصة قيادة لي.
There are a lot of people also --
وهناك عدد آخر من الأشخاص ايضا
very big support, like those 3,000 people
من الداعمين، كهؤلاء ال 3،000 شخص
who signed the petition to release me.
الذين وقعوا على الإلتماس من أجل إطلاق سراحي.
We sent a petition to the Shura Council
وقمنا بإرسال إلتماس إلى مجلس الشورى
in favor of lifting the ban on Saudi women,
من أجل أن يرفعوا هذا الحظر عن النساء السعوديات،
and there were, like, 3,500 citizens who believed in that
وكان هناك حوالي 3،500 مواطن من الذين آمنوا بهذا الأمر
and they signed that petition.
ووقعوا على تلك العريضة.
There were people like that, I just showed some examples,
وهناك العديد من الأشخاص مثل هؤلاء، ولكني هنا عرضت بضع امثلة فقط،
who are amazing, who are believing in women's rights in Saudi Arabia,
من الأشخاص الرائعون، الذين يؤمنون بحقوق المرأة في السعودية،
and trying, and they are also facing a lot of hate
والذين يحاولون، وهم أيضا يواجهون موجات قوية من الكراهية
because of speaking up and voicing their views.
فقط لأنهم يتحدثون ويطرحون أراءهم.
Saudi Arabia today is taking small steps
السعودية هذه الأيام تأخذ خطوات صغيرة
toward enhancing women's rights.
نحو تحسين حقوق المرأة.
The Shura Council that's appointed by the king,
مجلس الشورى المعيّن بواسطة الملك،
by royal decree of King Abdullah,
بمرسوم ملكي من الملك عبد الله،
last year there were 30 women assigned to that Council,
تم تعيين 30 امرأة فيه في العام الماضي،
like 20 percent.
والتي تمثل حوالي 20 بالمائة.
20 percent of the Council. (Applause)
20 بالمائة من المجلس. (تصفيق)
The same time, finally, that Council,
في هذه الأثناء، وأخيرا، ذلك المجلس،
after rejecting our petition four times for women driving,
وبعد أن رفض عريضتنا 4 مرات فيما يتعلق بقيادة المرأة،
they finally accepted it last February.
قاموا أخيرا بالموافقة عليها في فبراير الماضي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
After being sent to jail
بعد أن تم إرسالي إلى السجن
or sentenced lashing, or sent to a trial,
أو الحكم بالجلد، أو الإرسال إلى المحاكمة،
the spokesperson of the traffic police said,
فإن المتحدث الرسمي باسم شرطة المرور قال،
we will only issue traffic violation for women drivers.
بأننا سنقوم فقط بإصدار المخالفات المرورية للنساء في حالة القيادة.
The Grand Mufti, who is the head
المفتي الأعلى، وهو رئيس
of the religious establishment in Saudi Arabia,
الهيئة الدينية في السعودية،
he said, it's not recommended for women to drive.
قال أنه ليس من المستحب للنساء القيادة.
It used to be haram, forbidden, by the previous Grand Mufti.
لقد كانت حراما، ممنوعا، حسب المفتي الأعلى السابق.
So for me, it's not about only these small steps.
بالنسبة إلي، إنها ليست عن هذه الخطوات الصغيرة.
It's about women themselves.
إنها عن النساء أنفسهن.
A friend once asked me, she said,
سألتني صديقة في مرة، قالت:
"So when do you think this women driving will happen?"
"متى تعتقدين أن السماح للنساء بالقيادة سيحدث؟"
I told her, "Only if women stop asking 'When?'
أجبتها: "فقط عندما تتوقف النساء عن السؤال ’متى؟’
and take action to make it now."
وأن يقمن به الآن."
So it's not only about the system,
لذا هو ليس فقط عن النظام،
it's also about us women to drive our own life, I'd say.
إنه حولنا نحن النساء لنأخذ زمام حياتنا الخاصة، هذا ما أعتقده.
So I have no clue, really, how I became an activist.
حقيقة، لا فكرة لدي متى أصبحت ناشطة.
And I don't know how I became one now.
ولا أعرف كيف أصبحت واحدة الآن.
But all I know, and all I'm sure of, in the future
ولكن كل ما أعرفه، وكل ما متأكده منه، أنه في المستقبل
when someone asks me my story,
عندما يسألني شخص عن قصتي،
I will say, "I'm proud
سأقول: "أنا فخورة
to be amongst those women who lifted the ban,
بأنني كنت من تلكم النسوة اللاتي أزلن الحظر،
fought the ban, and celebrated everyone's freedom."
قاومن المنع، واحتفلن بحرية كل الناس."
So the question I started my talk with,
لذا فالسؤال الذي بدأت به حديثي هذا،
who do you think is more difficult to face,
من برأيكم تعتقدون أنه الأصعب في المجابهة،
oppressive governments or oppressive societies?
الحكومات القمعية أم المجتمعات القمعية؟
I hope you find clues to answer that from my speech.
أتمنى أنكم وجدتم الدلائل للإجابة عن هذا السؤال من حديثي هذا.
Thank you, everyone.
شكرا لكم، جميعا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)